<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: meta | Archetypal]]></title>
  <link href="http://archetyp.al/blog/categories/meta/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://archetyp.al/"/>
  <updated>2014-09-14T18:34:52-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://archetyp.al/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Rob Long]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Gypsies and Jet-setters: Bruce Sterling at 2006 SXSW]]></title>
    <link href="http://archetyp.al/blog/2013/03/06/gypsies-and-jet-setters-bruce-sterling-at-2006-sxsw/"/>
    <updated>2013-03-06T00:04:00-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://archetyp.al/blog/2013/03/06/gypsies-and-jet-setters-bruce-sterling-at-2006-sxsw</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This is the first Bruce Sterling talk that I encountered. Now I'm an inveterate Sterlingite, but at the time, 2006, I had only barely crossed intellectual paths with Sterling. I downloaded it with some long dead, precambrian cousin of google reader that lived in the swamps and estuaries of windows computers and survived by allowing the user to view RSS feeds on his desktop. Then pushed it to my equally antediluvian, single purpose device, an Archos mp3 player. I listened to this talk many times before the Archos died off. I thought this audio was lost to the bit bucket of history, until one day... <a href="http://archive.org/" title="archive dot org">archive.org</a>. These people are the new Library of Alexandria, with podcasts instead of papyrus.</p>

<p><a href="http://archive.org/details/BruceSterlingSxswKeynoteSpeechTheStateOfTheWorld" title="Bruce Sterling Sxsw Keynote, 2006 at archive.org">The full mp3 is available here.</a></p>

<!-- more -->


<p>Here are some excerpts:</p>

<p><blockquote><p>Commons based peer production, as an industrial method, is getting it's legs under it. This is something I complained about for years. I used to complain that GNU had the wrong name, because the recursive name for GNU is GNU's Not Unix. And I describe that as rather childish, because you should not name yourself in opposition to something else, you should have your own name. It's like, if GNU's not Unix, what is it?</p></p><p><p>Well, it's commons based peer production.</p></blockquote></p>

<p><blockquote><p>Flickr is not a copy of anything else. It is not a hippie knockoff of a commercial product. Wikipedia is not like anything else. A wiki is like nothing known to mankind. Collaborative web-filters are very spooky things; they are without historical precedent. Websites that throw their API's open and turn themselves into platforms rather than sites... it is a little hard to explain the significance of that to everyday people who are not techies and programmers, but that is a major development. The net community is no longer hanging on the coat-tails of Gates. That monopolistic chokehold, that did so much to reduce innovation, and to introduce global criminality to hapless Windows users.</p></blockquote></p>

<p><blockquote><p>Only in the United States do dying phone companies lobby the government as if they were indian casinos.</p></blockquote></p>

<p><blockquote><p>As you may or may not know, I am spending a lot of my time in Europe, after spending a year in California. I get to see America from the outside now. I get to see America as 94% of the planet sees America. And I look at wireless spreading in London and the spread of broadband in Korea. I've got broadband in Serbia where the phone companies are literally run by criminals in exile. And my broadband in Serbia costs $20 a month. And it works.</p></blockquote></p>

<p><blockquote><p>It is decadent, it is sclerotic. It looks like the Soviet Union.</p></p><p><p>...they are turning the USA into a banana republic with rockets.</p></p><p><p>Not just politically backward, <em>technically</em> backward.</p></blockquote></p>

<p><blockquote><p>The twenty first centry is definitely fertilizing my cyberpunk excentricities.</p></blockquote></p>

<p><blockquote><p>People ask me "have you moved to Belgrade? Is this permanent?" No, it's not permament. Just that, some of my shoes are there, and a closet... I live out of my laptop now. That's how I live. And so do increasing numbers of my collegues.</p></blockquote></p>

<p><blockquote><p>The twenty first centry is definitely fertilizing my cyberpunk excentricities.</p></blockquote></p>

<p><blockquote><p>It's a world of diaspora and globalization. Gypsies and jetsetters. Refugees and tech pioneers. And the differences are that thin.</p></blockquote></p>

<p><blockquote><p>I no longer need to be a resident of any particular city. I don't make any money in any foreign state. Nothing enters or leaves Belgrade except for ones and zeroes. That's all. I never stay there long enough to become permanent. I don't even DO permanent. National borders? They're like speed bumps.</p></blockquote></p>

<p>This talk is well composed. It is shot through with diamond bullets of poetic insight. Sterling's own voice and clearly communicated emotion turns this from a discursion on the quirks of Eastern Europe's up and coming intelligentsia into a full-blown harangue on the nature of the world as we find it right now in 2013, from the view of someone looking ahead in 2006.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Octopress CoderWall Aside]]></title>
    <link href="http://archetyp.al/blog/2012/07/08/octopress-coderwall-aside/"/>
    <updated>2012-07-08T22:22:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://archetyp.al/blog/2012/07/08/octopress-coderwall-aside</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>While attempting to embed the coderwall badges via the <a href="http://coderwall.com/api#blogbadge" title="coderwall badges">provided coderwall includes</a>, I found that the default coderwall css/javascript was not playing nicely with octopress. So, to the internets! There I found a nice post on this very topic, from the <a href="http://kagekirin.github.com/blog/2012/02/22/playing-with-octopress-custom-asides/" title="Code Alchemist">Code Alchemist</a> blog. He rolled his own solution, which even includes an "endorse" button. Not bad. Thanks!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Archetypical Post]]></title>
    <link href="http://archetyp.al/blog/2012/07/08/archetypical-post/"/>
    <updated>2012-07-08T13:04:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://archetyp.al/blog/2012/07/08/archetypical-post</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Picture a tree. Let's make it an <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Oak" title="Oak tree">oak tree</a>, so most people in the northern hemisphere will have direct access to one. Over the course of the oak tree's life, it increases in size gradually, with new branches, sub-branches, and leaves appearing in that order of frequency. The trunk remains alive, but is less dynamic in it's size and shape than the portions of the tree closer to the <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tree_(data_structure)" title="Tree_(data_structure)">leaf-nodes</a>, to borrow a metaphor that seems dangerously recursive. New branches and leaves appear and disappear, each with a frequency entirely contained by the structure supporting it on the tree. All of the leaves growing from a specific branch will be around no longer than the branch itself is around. So it is with the branch as well. If our example branch is attached to another larger branch, it will be part of the tree no longer than the larger branch is.</p>

<p>The tree is a familiar <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Archetype" title="archetype">archetype</a>. One can find similar instances of this archetype in other systems, from the <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tree_of_life_(biology)" title="tree of life">pattern of evolution</a> to <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Binary_tree" title="binary tree">data structures</a> in computer science. There is some utility in finding these archetypes and understanding them. We may find new insights into how to think about evolution, data storage, etc., by mining pre-existing sources of knowledge on similar systems. There is some risk associated with this behavior as well. It is always tempting to over-fit the metaphor and see <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Homology_(biology)" title="homology">homology</a> where there is no functional similarity.</p>

<p>I intend to use this site as a place to contain my thoughts on such matters, as well as a repository for my various projects. I will post on aspects of my projects that may illustrate the archetypes involved in software development and the design and implementation of systems in general. A primary source of inspiration for this site, including the title, is the book <a href="http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/0195019199/ref=as_li_ss_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;tag=archetypal-20&amp;linkCode=as2&amp;camp=1789&amp;creative=390957&amp;creativeASIN=0195019199" title="pattern language">A Pattern Language: Towns, Buildings, Construction</a> by Christopher Alexander.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
